Finding Aid for Woman's National Farm and Garden Association. Ann Arbor Branch records, 1946-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Woman's National Farm and Garden Association. Ann Arbor Branch records 1946-2011
Woman's National Farm and Garden Association. Ann Arbor Branch.
2 oversize volumes
2.75 linear feet
0143 Bk 2
Local branch of organization established to foster closer ties between city and country women and to stimulate interest in gardening and horticultural pursuits. Membership rosters, organizational files, historical information, files relating to fund raising and civic events, notably the Greens Market Sale and the Garden Walk tour of local gardens; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated to the library by the association (donor no. 8668 ) in 2000 and in later accessions.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Ann Arbor branch of the Woman's National Farm and Garden Association was established October 16, 1946. The stated purposes of the group were to foster a closer association between city women and country women and to stimulate interest in country life through educational assistance of students of agriculture, horticulture and forestry. Community service and charitable activities based upon gardening and horticultural pursuits remain a principal focus of the Ann Arbor branch.
The Ann Arbor branch conducts various fund raising activities each year to support its causes. Most prominent of these is the Greens Market, a pre-Christmas sale of holiday decorations. Fresh garland is brought in from Northern Michigan associates of the group to be sold. The sale has expanded over the years to include all types of holiday decorations and baked goods and raises much of the branch's charitable budget. Another activity of the branch is the Gardenwalk, a tour of Ann Arbor homes and their gardens. The branch also conducts smaller activities such as dinners, teas, exhibits and speeches.
Money raised by the Ann Arbor branch is used to support a number of educational and charitable causes. The branch supports two scholarships at the University of Michigan's School of Natural Resources and Environment for students of agriculture, horticulture and forestry. The branch also contributes to a number of the School's research activities, including forestry camps in northern Michigan. The branch also supports Ann Arbor area institutions and museums, including U of M's Matthaei Botanical Gardens.
The records of the Woman's National Farm and Garden Association, Ann Arbor Branch, document all of the group's various organizational and community service activities. They reflect the organization's dedication to community service through scholarships, charitable gifts and service activities. The records have been divided into five series: History, Yearbooks, Organizational, Photographs, and Events.
Subjects:
Woman's National Farm and Garden Association. Ann Arbor Branch.; Gardening--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Woman's National Farm and Garden Association. Ann Arbor Branch.; Flower shows--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gardening--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Organizations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History 1948-1999
  The History series (1946-1998; 0.25 linear feet) contains information about the history of the national organization and the Ann Arbor branch, including various history projects produced by members. Also included is The Chronicle: A History of the Woman's National Farm and Garden Association, Martha Nolan's work documenting the history and activities of the national association. A scrapbook produced by the branch and begun in 1954 includes reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings and photographs felt by members to be representative of the branch's past.
  - History: Fifty Years of Greens Market 1948-1998 (Box 1)
  - A Chronicle: The History of the Woman's National Farm and Garden Association 1914-1984 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks containing clippings, photographs and correspondence 1954-1999, 2 oversize volumes (Volume 1)
- Yearbooks 1948-2008
  The Yearbook series (1948-2008; 0.25 linear feet) contains rosters of the branch's membership spanning the majority of its existence. The rosters include name and address of all members as well as listing of branch officers and terms of service.
  - Yearbooks 1948 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks 1950-1969 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks 1970-1989 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks 1999-2008 (Box 1)
- Organizational 1946-2011
  The Organizational series (1946-2011; 1.25 linear feet) documents all of the routine activities required to maintain the organization. Included are meeting minutes, financial reports, awards, committee reports, promotional materials, correspondence, newsletters and receipts. The activities of each segment of the branch are documented in detail, giving a comprehensive look at the branch as a whole.
  - Awards 1986-2005 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1953-1997 (Box 1)
  - Civic Projects 1958-1994 (Box 1)
  - Conservation Committee 1957-1988 (Box 1)
  - Conservation 1978-1988 (Box 1)
  - Corresponding Secretary 1977-1990 (Box 1)
  - Education/Scholarships 1952-1996 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports 1947-1995 and 2009, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Foundation Budget 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Horticultural Therapy 1962-1990 (Box 1)
  - Hospitality Committee 1982-1994 (Box 1)
  - International Committee 1953-1989 (Box 1)
  - Membership Committee 1982-1990 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1946-1994, 2000-2009, 8 folders; 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Newsletter 1976-1998 (Box 2)
  - President's Reports 1949-1999 (Box 2)
  - Program Committee 1958-1987 (Box 2)
  - Program Books 1975-1981 (Box 2)
  - Publicity 1949-1997 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Correspondence 1979-1989 (Box 2)
  - Thank You Notes 1979-1989 (Box 2)
  - Yearbook Committee 1963-1990 (Box 2)
  - Later records 2010-2011 (Box 2)
- Photographs 1954-1998
  The Photograph series (1954-1998; 0.25 linear feet) consists of two folders of photographs of members and activities. Most are from 1977-1998 although a number of earlier photographs are included.
  - Photographs 1954, 1964, 1970, 1977-1988 (Box 3)
  - Photographs 1990-1998 (Box 3)
- Events 1948-2005
  The Events series (1948-2005, 0.75 linear foot) documents the various fund raising and civic events sponsored by the Ann Arbor branch. Most prominent of these is the Greens Market, a pre-Christmas sale of fresh greens held annually by the branch. Also included are the records of Garden Walk, a tour of local homes and their gardens arranged annually by the branch and a 1975 flower show.
  - Greens Market 1948-1997, 27 folders (Box 3)
  - Gardenwalk 1991-2005, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Flower Show 1975 (Box 3)